<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The friendly interposer, between the authors of those papers, the one called a report, the other, a rebuke of that report in order to a sound reconciliation between the Presbyterians and Independents in doctrinals, by the proposal of a third way, when both of them in their own, are out / by John Humphrey.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16381</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12859595</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12859595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94658</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94658)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The friendly interposer, between the authors of those papers, the one called a report, the other, a rebuke of that report in order to a sound reconciliation between the Presbyterians and Independents in doctrinals, by the proposal of a third way, when both of them in their own, are out / by John Humphrey.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Williams, Daniel, 1643?-1716. --  Answer to the report, &amp;c., which the united ministers appointed their commitee to draw up.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94658:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Friendly Interpoſer,</hi> BETWEEN THE Authors of thoſe <hi>Papers,</hi> the one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>A Report;</hi> the other, <hi>A Rebuke</hi> of that <hi>Report.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN ORDER TO A Sound Reconciliation between the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> in Doctrinals, by the Propoſal of a <hi>Third Way,</hi> when both of them in their own, are out.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MFREY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And Abraham ſaid unto Lot, let there be no Strife I pray thee, between Thee and Me, and between my Herdmen and thy Herd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for we are Brethren,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 13.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel, 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94658:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94658:2"/>
            <head>THE Friendly Interpoſer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>Report</hi> —</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have put out a Sheet Entituled, <hi>a Report of the Preſent State of the Differences in Doctrinals, between ſome Diſſenting Miniſters in</hi> London; and there is about five Sheets written in Anſwer to You, called <hi>A Rebuke.</hi> The Names of the Authors are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed (which is beſt, for why ſhould the Names of Brethren be claſhed one againſt another) and I call you therefore Mr. <hi>Report</hi> upon that account, craving ſome of your Patience, as to a little I have to ſay to you. This <hi>Antagoniſt</hi> of yours is a ſmart Man I muſt needs ſay, and while he pleaſes himſelf, and others, and me, with his Wit, I would have you take part with us, and be pleaſed too, and moved no more than if it were writ on another Man. He is I confeſs too Magiſterial, through an over Prejudice, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue of him he writes againſt: But let that be your Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, for beſides that, <hi>Better is it to be humble in Spirit, than proud in Spirit;</hi> it will be ſome <hi>Victory</hi> to you, if you be <hi>unmoved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two things to be conſidered in this Book of his, what he hath <hi>Ad hominem,</hi> and what <hi>Ad rem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad hominem,</hi> two things likewiſe are to be conſidered, what he tells, as the <hi>Narrative</hi> he gives (which is the chief buſineſs of his Book) for juſtifying the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and what he has to ſay in Particular in Reference to you.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Narration</hi> of Matters he gives us, I thank him. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve every thing he ſays, and every thing you ſay, for neither of you I am aſſured will lye: Nevertheleſs, whether the Policy of the <hi>Piſmire,</hi> he ſo prettily applies to you in nibbling off ſomething of the Story, be not incidental to him alſo I Queſtion; becauſe the chief Matter which made the noiſe, as to the Difference among you, which was the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſeparating from the Lecture in <hi>Pinners-Hall</hi> to another Place, is not accounted for by Mr. <hi>Rebuke.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94658:3"/>Not that it is done by either out of Falſhood, but Caution, for avoiding ill Conſequents, for in regard that neither of you, one or other; but do look upon the Breach effected, as an evil thing, and that they were faulty who made it; it is more adviſable on all Hands, to endeavour rather to make up the Breach, and mend the Fault, than to trouble one another in finding out where it is moſt to be laid. If you can come to agree again, the twelve Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Preachers ſhould joyn in one Lecture in the old Place, that what proclaimed the <hi>Diviſion</hi> may be the Token of your <hi>Coali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It appears by your <hi>Sheet,</hi> that there was ſix or ſeven of the more eminent of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> that pitcht upon the Printed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in that Sheet, as a means to bring both Parties, <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> to a Re-union; and they began themſelves with the Subſcribing it, but neither would the more Eminent of the <hi>Independents,</hi> nor the reſt of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren follow them; ſo that another Paper was provided by a ſingle Perſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rejected, and a <hi>Third</hi> Compoſed by ſuch as were appointed for the Work; and this <hi>Third Paper</hi> is to be Propoſed for an <hi>Accommodation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What that <hi>Third Paper</hi> is I never ſaw, but ſuppoſing it ſuch as is more ſatisfactory than either of the other; I will tell you what I think I ſhould be bound to do, if I were you, in the Buſineſs. You are one that to bring your <hi>Independent</hi> Party in, have taken much Pains, and uſed ſo much Art, that you have loſt that eſteem of a <hi>Pacificator</hi> (as you call theſe ſix or ſeven before mentioned) and are thought to be the Perſon that undermines the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> which you pretend to Reſtore: You are therefore (knowing your own Conſcience toward God and Peace) to let the Brethren know that ſeeing this way, which you and the ſix or ſeven wiſer than you imagined, would have done the Deed, hath failed you; it ſhall not lye at your Door, but that another be tried; and (if upon reading their <hi>Third Paper,</hi> you find nothing in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience againſt it) that you are the ſame Perſon, and concur with them in it, and with the ſame Reſolution as you took up in your Letter to Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> concerning Mr. <hi>Williams;</hi> to wit, that if he would agree in his Doctrine with that <hi>Doctor,</hi> and the reſt of the Brethren; you would Compound with him, if not yet <hi>with him, or without him,</hi> you would reſolve, ſo far as you could, to get a Compoſition. It was bravely ſpoken then, if you do now the ſame thing in regard to your <hi>Independent</hi> Brethren; for ſeeing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94658:3"/>Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> is now come to Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> or Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> to Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> (which is all one) in their Agreement on this <hi>Third Paper,</hi> together with the reſt of the ſix or ſeven that Signed the firſt, and the Body of the Brethren of the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> if there be any one or two <hi>Independents,</hi> or other ſtand out, and will not come in, you muſt let them alone; and be reſolved, <hi>whether with them or without them, according to the moſt Chriſtian Reſolution of ſome worthy Brethren of both Perſwaſions,</hi> to come to a Coalition.</p>
            <p>As for the other thing <hi>Ad hominem,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> has a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, it is your eſpouſing ſo much as you do thoſe <hi>Phraſes</hi> (he calls them) of a <hi>Commutation of Perſons, Chriſt ſuſtaining our Perſon, putting on the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> and the like; which he ſays are only <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phraſes, (though <hi>induere,</hi> and <hi>exuere Perſonam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cujus</hi> is good Latin, if your Senſe) and while he makes ſo <hi>light</hi> of them as needleſs, and you ſo <hi>much,</hi> it is like you will be diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: But I warn you of that, for ſeeing he does fully grant all that <hi>Grotius,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> do underſtand by this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation,</hi> you muſt make theſe Phraſes of more Signification than they, or elſe you ſtand upon meer Words, which is little. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, there is one thing I will ſay of Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> that you will hardly think I ſhould. I do believe that he was one of the ſix or ſeven Eminent Brethren that Signed your firſt Paper for Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet does he ſet this <hi>Phraſe</hi> in that Paper almoſt at naught, which you ſtand ſo much upon, becauſe it is there. Here now will ſome ſay, we have a Man for a thing and againſt it; is not this baſe, to be ſo mutable? I ſay no, but this is generous, and free; and therefore ſo, upon that very account. For ſo long as any ſuch Term, Word or <hi>Phraſe</hi> was like to tend to the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Peace, he is <hi>free</hi> to let you make as much of it as you could, but when he ſees it not conducive to the end, but the contrary, he is <hi>free</hi> to ſpeak out <hi>himſelf,</hi> and make as little of it. If they were <hi>Words of Scripture,</hi> he would <hi>captivare intellectum</hi> to ſome right Conſtruction of them, but when they are only <hi>Terms of Men,</hi> he will be no <hi>Slave</hi> to any, but uſe them, or leave them, as Good or Evil is like to come of them. But to go on, Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> tells us, that there is neither in the <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> nor any <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches any ſuch Phraſe to be found, and I take it upon truſt from him, becauſe <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf has not this Phraſe full out; who ſays indeed, there is <hi>a Commutatio, a ſubrogatio, a ſubſtitutio</hi> (theſe Words he uſes) of Chriſts Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in our room as to his Sufferings for us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vice noſtra,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94658:4"/>in our ſtead, as the Sacrifice died in the ſtead of the Sinner that Sacrificed it; but a <hi>Commutation of Perſons</hi> full out, he has not, nor any authority from the Ancients any farther than thus: <hi>Deus pro animabus omnium dedit Commutationem pretioſum ſanguinem filii ſui;</hi> which is <hi>Origen. Dominus noſter Jeſus Chriſtus communicando nobiſcum ſine culpa poenam, &amp; culpam ſolvit &amp; poenam;</hi> which is <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> There is not a Quotation of his elſe, hath any touch of ſuch a Phraſe; and who ſhall come after <hi>Grotius</hi> to look for any thing he hath miſt? I cloſe therefore here with this Reverend Brother. <hi>This Phraſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>of Chriſt's taking on him the Perſon of Sinners, does ſignifie more or leſs than Chriſt's taking on him our Sins, and ſuffering for them in our place or ſtead; or it does ſignifie neither more nor leſs, but is juſt commenſurate with it. If you make it ſignifie leſs, then it limits and narrows the end of Chriſt's Suffering, and will be a ſenſe only ſerving the turn of the</hi> Socinian: <hi>If you make it ſignifie more than that, it leads to</hi> Antinomianiſm: <hi>If it ſignifies (or be made to ſignifie) neither more nor leſs, I embrace it with all my Heart.</hi> This Gentleman does ſtill ſpeak wittily; but here wittily and ſolidly, and I fully aſſent to it.</p>
            <p>I won't ſay that <hi>you</hi> do, when we are now come from what he hath had, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> to what he ſhould have <hi>ad rem.</hi> A Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is in <hi>Doctrinals,</hi> as to this point, among the Brethren, and the buſineſs to be done, is to find the bottom of it, and to ſay ſomething which is not ſaid by this Brother, for ſatisfaction to it. It is true, that though there be no more to be put upon theſe Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (I believe) than <hi>Grotius,</hi> and the aforeſaid <hi>Biſhop</hi> puts upon them, yet are there very Learned Men, ſuch as among us are <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therford</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who I ſuppoſe, together with you, do lay more upon them than ſo, when there are others (if not they) do carry them ſo far as to hold this <hi>Commutation</hi> to be ſuch, that from thence it is they account, not only that our Sins are laid upon Chriſt, but his Righteouſneſs is communicated to us, which is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us to <hi>ſuſtain his Perſon,</hi> as well as he <hi>ours,</hi> and we thereby made Righteous as he, in the Eye of the Law, or in Law-ſenſe for our Juſtification. And this now I take to be another Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt obey'd the Law, and ſuffer'd for us in our behalf, or in our ſtead, ſo as God looks upon us to have ſuffered the Penalty of the Law in him to free us from Condemnation, and to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the Law in him to give us right to Heaven, which your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of Perſons,</hi> at the leaſt muſt ſignifie; then are we in Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94658:4"/>indeed <hi>Legally</hi> righteous, (for this is to be righteous in Law-ſenſe, or in the Eye of the Law, that is <hi>Legally ſo,</hi> if they know what to be <hi>Legally Righteous</hi> is) and accordingly juſtified by the <hi>Law</hi> with his Righteouſneſs, as our formal Righteouſneſs, or as the <hi>Form,</hi> or <hi>Formal Cauſe,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> of our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> This is the Opinion, which in behalf of your <hi>Independent</hi> Brethren, you do and muſt maintain, as that which hath been received for the common <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Opinion heretofore, and if it be true, muſt bring your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries over to you, or elſe if it be not true, both you and they muſt look for a righter, in a middle way between <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Papiſt,</hi> which I doubt, the moſt of you are either too negligent to ſeek, or too conceited (through your own greater learning) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive at another's Hands. <hi>Sententia illorum qui Chriſti obedientiam &amp; juſtitiam nobis imputatam ſtatuunt eſſe formalem cauſam juſtificationis, communis eſt noſtrorum omnium ſententia, neque quod ad rem attinet, quiſquam è noſtris aliter ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t aut ſcripſit,</hi> ſays <hi>Davenant, ds Juſ. Hab.</hi> c. 22.</p>
            <p>Well now, if the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt be indeed the <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification as this Learned Man, and moſt Judicious Man otherwiſe, does maintain for the received <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Doctrine, and which thoſe <hi>Independent</hi> Brethren, who upon the account of <hi>Doctrinals,</hi> hang off from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> will approve, or elſe they know not what they would have to ſtrive for, then muſt we be <hi>Legally righteous</hi> in Chriſt, and ſo juſtified by the <hi>Law.</hi> And if the <hi>Believer</hi> be in Chriſt <hi>Legally righteous,</hi> then muſt Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be the <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of his Juſtification. They that ſay one, muſt ſay the other; and they that deny the one, muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the other, if they underſtand fundamentally what they are to affirm or deny. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> held inherent Grace, as infuſed to be the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification: The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in oppoſition maintain'd, That Chriſt's Righteouſneſs without us, and not ours within us, imputed to <hi>us,</hi> is that which <hi>formally</hi> juſtifies us. To be juſtified then by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, is to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Chriſt in <hi>Law-ſenſe;</hi> and to be righteous in Chriſt in Law-ſenſe, or in the Eye of the Law, is to be look'd on by God to have undergone the Penalty of the Law in Chriſt's Sufferings, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the Law in Chriſt's Obedience, and this infers a <hi>Commutation of Perſons</hi> in the higheſt ſenſe, which you and your <hi>Brethren</hi> do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed intend by it.</p>
            <p>Here then we are come to the bottom which the Reverend and Ingenious Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> has not ſounded, and here is the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94658:5"/>upon which the fundamental Difference between you, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the <hi>Independants</hi> and your Adverſaries, does bottom. If this Doctrine be true, then muſt the Conſequences of it be true? If the Conſequences be not good, the Doctrine muſt not be good neither.</p>
            <p>Let us then come Hand to Hand to the Tryal. If your Doctrine be true, That there is ſuch a Commutation of <hi>Perſons</hi> as that God does look on us in Chriſt's Perſon, to have ſuffered the Puniſhment, and obeyed the Law, and ſo to be in him <hi>Legally righteous</hi> and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by his Righteouſneſs <hi>Formaliter,</hi> according to the Law of Works, then muſt his Righteouſneſs be ours; ſo that in a Legal ſenſe, we muſt be as righteous as he, or God muſt look on us in him as <hi>righteous as he,</hi> and then can God ſee no ſin in the Believer, and the Believer have no need of Repentance, or other Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with the like Inferences, which we utterly condemn (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by the moſt pious of them mitigated) in the <hi>Antinomian.</hi> The Conſequence really is not to be denied, unleſs by outfacing it with number, or ſhifting. Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe</hi> acknowledges, if we be <hi>formally</hi> juſtified by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, then are we as righteous as he; and therefore he will have his Righteouſneſs to be the <hi>Matter,</hi> not the <hi>Form</hi> of our Juſtification: And <hi>Ameſius</hi> being put to it by this Objection from <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> apprehends the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſo irrefragable, that he recedes from the Doctrine. <hi>Haec non eſt noctra ſententia,</hi> (ſays he hereupon) though <hi>Davenant</hi> you ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, does ſtoutly affirm the contrary. And when it becomes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to recede from <hi>this Doctrine,</hi> it is fit we find out <hi>another</hi> that will hold better together.</p>
            <p>If in good earneſt you will maintain this <hi>Doctrine of Commutation,</hi> ſo that you underſtand no leſs by it than this, That Chriſt hath obey'd and ſuffer'd in our Perſon, that the Law is obeyed and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by us in him, or we Legally righteous in him (which is all one,) I argue farther, as in my <hi>Pacification,</hi> and who ſhall anſwer it? If this were ſo, Then ſhould we not our ſelves obey at all, Then ſhould we not ſuffer at all; for he that hath perfectly obeyed, can be puniſhed for nothing; Then ſhould we need no forgiveneſs; Then would Chriſt's Suffering for us, having obey'd, be needleſs; Then muſt he be look'd on by God as a ſinner; Then muſt the <hi>Culpa</hi> as well as the <hi>Poena</hi> be imputed to him; Then could not Chriſt be our Mediator, becauſe he is look'd on as the Offending Party, and a Mediator is a third Party between the Offender and the Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in which Perſon he obeyed and ſuffered for us: Then laſtly,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94658:5"/>ſhould Impunity and Life be due to us immediately by a meer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultancy from his Obedience and Sufferings, and not be given by the interpoſition of a new Law or Covenant upon Terms as they are according to the Goſpel, which is ſubverted therefore by this Opinion.</p>
            <p>I pray then Mr. <hi>Report</hi> will you ſit down a little with me and conſider what you would have by this <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> and ſee if it will hold. There are two Points according to you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon it, which are the principal Points in the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; to wit, <hi>Chriſt's Satisfaction,</hi> and <hi>our Juſtification.</hi> But here it is that you are out with the Brethren, and the excellent Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> who all of you do build this <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> upon that Union with Chriſt, which we call the <hi>Myſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between Chriſt and the Elect Believer, by vertue whereof, and not otherwiſe, Chriſt's Righteouſneſs (you count) becomes theirs for their Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. But, Sir, this cannot be; for if Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be ours, as thus <hi>One with him,</hi> then muſt it be one and the ſame Righteouſneſs, and we righteous as he (as before in God's Eye, or in the Eye of the Law, which is all one. His Righteouſneſs is imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> and we juſtified by the Law with his Righteouſneſs (as I have ſaid) as the <hi>Form</hi> it ſelf, or <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            <p>That being obſerved (as you will yet ſee more) and thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (contained in the Eight <hi>Then's</hi>) unanſwerable, it is your miſtake, therefore here with others to ſuppoſe ſuch a <hi>Commutation</hi> as is built upon this <hi>Myſtical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> when there is none but what is founded on his <hi>Hypoſtatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> which concerns all <hi>Mankind,</hi> as well as the <hi>Elect,</hi> and anſwers this full ſenſe of <hi>Grotius</hi> mentioned before. Of which point in particular I will forbear ſaying more, becauſe I have endeavoured to make this out in a Chapter I have in my <hi>Peaceable Diſquiſitions</hi> on Purpoſe againſt Dr. <hi>Owen;</hi> which Book I preſented to the Doctor, while living, and he never writ againſt it. See my <hi>Pacif.</hi> alſo, <hi>Pag.</hi> 16, and there is ſome Epitomy of it.</p>
            <p>One thing yet I will tell you in regard to thoſe two great Points mentioned; that however commodious and proper you think theſe Phraſes be for the making out the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> (if you uſe them in no other ſenſe than that of <hi>Grotius</hi>) in regard to <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm:</hi> they are as much incommodious and dangerous, I fear, for the making out the Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification</hi> (if hey be uſed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the common <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) in regard to <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi> They
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94658:6"/>are not equally applicable, I muſt ſay, to both; for it is ſufficient that Chriſt took on him our Nature, and ſo put his <hi>Natural</hi> Perſon in our room in ſuffering for us, to make out the one; but he muſt be myſtically put into <hi>our,</hi> and we into <hi>his Legal Perſon,</hi> to make out the other.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this Phraſe, there are two Queſtions I muſt ask; One of <hi>you,</hi> and the other of Mr. <hi>Rebuke,</hi> or elſe your two Alterca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about it will ſignifie nothing. The Queſtion I would ask Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> is this; Whether he did deſignedly intend a Difference between a <hi>Change of Perſon,</hi> and a <hi>Change of Perſons?</hi> Which he ſeems to have done by ſome expreſs Words; and his meaning then muſt be, That tho' Chriſt came into the room of Sinners to ſuffer for them, and may be accordingly ſaid to ſuſtain their perſons, or to put on their Perſons; yet the Sinner does not come into the room of Chriſt's Perſon, or ſuſtain his Perſon, or take on him his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and conſequently that there is a change of <hi>Perſon,</hi> but not of <hi>Perſons</hi> between them. If this be his ſenſe and not ſpoke out of a preſent Sagacity or Wit, but upon a deliberate Reſolution, it is a great matter. I have touched upon this in my <hi>Pacif.</hi> and in an <hi>Half-ſheet</hi> printed by it ſelf. But here it may be required of Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> to ſhew ſome Author of note for ſuch a diſtinction, which would fix it, but he will find none I doubt, only Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams;</hi> and here is the miſchief of that. Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> denying that there is a <hi>Change of Perſon between Christ and the Elect,</hi> does account himſelf wrong'd, to have that interpreted, no <hi>Change of Perſons;</hi> ſo that he holds a <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> and denies only a <hi>Change of Perſon;</hi> when Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> directly contrary allows a <hi>Change of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> but denies a <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> and yet both intend the ſame ſenſe. I on purpoſe noted this in that Half-ſheet mentioned, and told there Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s Senſe; and I know Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> had that Half-ſheet, and he would have done well to have quoted it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when many Hands are required to a Work, it is better accept any meaner Hand, than<note n="*" place="margin">This <hi>Half-ſheet</hi> therefore ſhall be Printed at the end.</note> none at all. For the Queſtion now I have to ask you Mr. <hi>Report,</hi> it is this: That granting you to be in the right, as to the Phraſe <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> which theſe two chief Learned Men, Biſhop <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> for a <hi>Conformist,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> for a <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> do uſe and warrant; I muſt demand only what is your ſenſe of it? You muſt tell me ſuch a ſenſe of this <hi>Change,</hi> as that the Sinner muſt come in the room of Chriſt, as well as Chriſt in the room of the Sinner. If you have thought on ſuch a ſenſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94658:6"/>before you wrote, as to be fixed in it, you are a Man of <hi>Judgment,</hi> and if you can maintain it when fixed, you are a Man of <hi>Might.</hi> If you can fetch that ſenſe out of <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> that moſt Learned Biſhop is alive, and will make it good, and it is like to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; if you fetch it out of <hi>Owen,</hi> that excellent Doctor is dead, and you muſt make it good your ſelf. And I would have you take heed of that, for you ſee Eight Arguments you muſt encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which if they be enlarged and drawn out in Battle their Strength will be great. I muſt alſo yet tell you; that in my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion verily <hi>Grotius</hi> (whatſoever you imagine) does verge to Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> rather than you; becauſe in his ſhewing, that the Prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when applied to Perſons does import this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation,</hi> and inſtances in <hi>Archelaus</hi>'s coming in the room of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod;</hi> I cannot believe that <hi>Grotius</hi> ever once thought of <hi>Herod</hi>'s coming in the room of <hi>Archelaus;</hi> ſo that the Point between you muſt come to this; that whereas you both are agreed, that <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelaus</hi> came in the room of <hi>Herod;</hi> you are to ſhew in what Senſe <hi>Herod</hi> came alſo in <hi>Archelaus</hi>'s room, or you are gone. In ſhort, Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> grants you ſuch a <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> as the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one in the room of the other; but not ſuch, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of both in the room of one another.</p>
            <p>To be more clear in reſpect to Mr. <hi>Rebuke,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> in the Notion before; I will take Liberty to expreſs my ſelf in my own Terms. There is a Threefold <hi>Perſon,</hi> a <hi>Natural</hi> Perſon, a <hi>Qualitative</hi> Perſon, and a <hi>Repreſentative</hi> Perſon. The <hi>Natural</hi> Perſon is that we call in Metaphyſicks <hi>ſuppoſitum rationale,</hi> ſuch as <hi>John, Peter, You,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> which every one knows. The <hi>Qualita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Perſon is the <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> of the Natural Perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is, as one Man is a <hi>Juſtice,</hi> another a <hi>Conſtable,</hi> another a <hi>King.</hi> If a Prince (ſays <hi>Barclay</hi>) ſhall go to deſtroy his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Si regnum alienet, ſi Rem publicam evertere conetur,</hi> he does <hi>exuere Perſonam Regis,</hi> and he ceaſing to be King, our Subjection ceaſes. This I bring only to ſhew you what a <hi>Qualitative</hi> Perſon is. A <hi>Repreſentative</hi> Perſon, is one that in what he does or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, repreſents another, or does it in his ſtead; and this <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative</hi> Perſon is twofold, <hi>Real,</hi> or <hi>Hiſtrionical.</hi> A Real Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Perſon, is that we call a <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Perſon; who is one that Acts ſo in another's Room, that the Perſon for whom he Acts, is to be accounted to have done it in his Perſon, it being valid, and as good in <hi>Law,</hi> as if himſelf had done it. As what an <hi>Atturney</hi> at Law does for his <hi>Client,</hi> or a <hi>Guardian</hi> for his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94658:7"/>
               <hi>Pupil,</hi> it is accounted in Law to be done by <hi>Client</hi> and <hi>Pupil,</hi> ſo that they may in thoſe Acts be ſaid to <hi>ſuſtain their Perſons.</hi> Thus a <hi>Parliament</hi> is the Repreſentative of the <hi>Nation.</hi> An <hi>Hiſtrioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Fictitious,</hi> or <hi>feigned</hi> Perſon, is one that Acts the <hi>Qualitatives Perſon,</hi> or imitates his Qualities; as the Man on the Stage that Acts a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Porter,</hi> does <hi>Perſonate</hi> or <hi>put on the Perſon</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Porter,</hi> when he is neither. Now when Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> in his Book, denies a <hi>change of Perſon</hi> between Chriſt and the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (or the Elect, for the Elect are Sinners) yet grants a change of <hi>Perſons,</hi> he muſt be ſo underſtood, That he denies, Chriſt took on him the <hi>Qualitative</hi> Perſon of a Sinner, or was ſo accounted of God; and likewiſe, that he did not Act the Part of Sinners, or do what they do, which is certainly true; and yet that there is a <hi>change of Perſons,</hi> is regard to our <hi>Natural</hi> Perſons betwixt Chriſt and us; for Chriſt in his natural Perſon came in the room of our Natural Perſons, and ſuffered for our Deliverance. Thus much muſt be undoubtedly ſo, but as for the <hi>Real Repreſentative</hi> now, there is the Queſtion; Whether Chriſt took on him our <hi>Legal</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Perſon, ſo that we are to be look'd on, as having done and ſuffered in him as our <hi>legal Perſon,</hi> what he did and ſuffered, whereby his <hi>very Righteouſneſs</hi> muſt be ours in <hi>Law-ſenſe</hi> for our Juſtification. This I take to be the Common Opinion of the Proteſtant, and which you have received. But this I deny. This Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> denies, whether Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> does or no, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult his Books. My Reaſons for the denial are thoſe eight <hi>Thens</hi> already ſaid, unto which more may be added. <hi>They do heinouſly erre</hi> (ſays Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>and ſubvert the Goſpel, who ſay that Christ's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is ſo imputed to us, as that God reputeth Christ to have been perfectly Holy and ſuffered, though not in our Natural, yet in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal or Civil Perſon of the Sinner, or Believer; as their ſtrict and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Repreſenter, and ſo to have our ſelves fulfilled all Righteouſneſs in him or by him,</hi> and thereby be juſtified: There are more Words by Way of Aggravation, which I fill up with [<hi>and thereby be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified.</hi>] I know you have cited formerly ſome Paſſages, and may again, out of Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Williams;</hi> but I pray conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how they are more oppoſite to Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and I will therefore ſay thus much about them. I remember in Reading <hi>Luther</hi> againſt King <hi>Henry,</hi> who had wrote a Book againſt him, how in one or two places, upon the King's urging ſome Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of little weight, he diſtinguiſhes thus upon him. Such a thing (I have forgot what) may be taken (ſays he) <hi>Dupliciter,</hi> theſe <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94658:7"/>either <hi>Revera,</hi> or <hi>Henericaliter.</hi> I muſt anſwer ſo here, that if thoſe Paſſages, or the like of Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> be taken <hi>Henericaltter,</hi> as the <hi>Words</hi> of that beloved Dr. they muſt paſs, becauſe he hath ſaid them; but if they be taken <hi>Revera</hi> (the Expreſſions being Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and not heeded) the <hi>Senſe</hi> of them muſt be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, according to Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Term <hi>Surety</hi> which you farther ſtand upon, there are many ſorts of <hi>Sureties,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells you, and what <hi>kind</hi> a one, <hi>Christ</hi> is; which you know well enough (<hi>Cath. Theol.</hi> Part II. <hi>p.</hi> 66.), ſo that you muſt not take the Word, and uſe it in ſo groſs a Senſe as it hath been commonly, as if Chriſt and we were in the ſame Bond, and the Debt being paid by him, the whole Obligation is to be preſently cancelled all one as if we had paid it our ſelves. Such a <hi>Surety</hi> in effect is the ſame thing as to be our <hi>Legal Perſon,</hi> and a <hi>Legal Perſon</hi> as ſuch a <hi>Surety;</hi> and therefore upon the ſame Reaſons not to be admitted. Beſides, to have <hi>lhe Debt paid</hi> is one thing, and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> only <hi>made</hi> is another. <hi>Solutio ejuſdem,</hi> and <hi>redditio equivalentis aliter indebiti,</hi> are two things with <hi>Scotus,</hi> and inconſiſtent with one another. <hi>Cum alius ſoluit</hi> (you know <hi>Grotius</hi>) <hi>aliud ſoluitur.</hi> Moreover the Term <hi>Surety</hi> is but once read, but the Word <hi>Mediator</hi> ſeveral times, and that which is more frequent, muſt give the Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the other. Chriſt's <hi>Suretiſhip</hi> is a <hi>Mediatory Suretiſhip,</hi> or a <hi>Surety-Mediatorſhip,</hi> and what he did and ſuffered for us, was not therefore ſtrictly done in <hi>our Perſons,</hi> but in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of a <hi>Mediator;</hi> and that not by Way of <hi>Payment,</hi> but by Way of <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> in Order to the obtaining our Reconciliation with God, from whence it is, that of the <hi>new Covenant</hi> he is ſaid to be <hi>Surety</hi> and <hi>Mediator,</hi> as thereby procuring it for us. So in my <hi>Pacif.</hi> p. 15. And yet there is this one thing more, the moſt undeniable; to wit, that in whatſoever Senſe he was our <hi>Surety,</hi> it muſt be ſuch as is agreeable to the general Doctrine of the Scripture, ſo as to croſs nothing of that it hath taught. Now that Chriſt hath <hi>redeemed all Mankind</hi> according to the <hi>Churches Catechiſm,</hi> that he hath dyed for <hi>all,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.) for <hi>every Man,</hi> (<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.) for the <hi>whole World</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2.) is certain Scripture, and there muſt be ſome Senſe, wherein it is to be admitted of all Hands. In that Senſe therefore, or in ſuch a Senſe as is conſiſtent with the <hi>Grace of God, that bringeth Salvation to all Men,</hi> that is, with <hi>this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> muſt the <hi>Suretiſhip of</hi> Chriſt be underſtood and received;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94658:8"/>and in any other Senſe not conſiſtent with this <hi>Grace of God,</hi> or this Doctrine, it is to be Refuſed; as contrary to the Goſpel, and all good Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Thus much being ſaid as to the <hi>Matter,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Phraſe</hi> of <hi>Commutation of Perſons.</hi> I will for Peace ſake yield to you, and I will yield to Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> both. I yield to you, that you are in the Right as to the <hi>Phraſe,</hi> and I will ſay as much for it (you ſhall preſently ſee) as can be, and I yield to him, that he is in the Right as to the <hi>ſubstantial Senſe;</hi> and therefore do I proceed. There are three Conſtructions may be made of this <hi>Commutation</hi> of Perſons. One is, that Chriſt taking on him our Nature, hath dyed to ſatisfie the Juſtice of God in behalf of us, as the Sacrifices of Old; and the <hi>Commutation of Perſons</hi> in this Senſe muſt be underſtood thus, that whereas Chriſt was an Innocent Perſon, and ſo not liable to Suffering, and we were Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and obnoxious; Chriſt here comes in the room of the Obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious, and ſuffers, putting us in the room of him that was not obnoxious and not lyable, to eſcape upon the Terms of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. This Conſtruction in ſhort comes to this. <hi>Christ ſuffers, that we might not ſuffer;</hi> and this is the true and only Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (I think) of this <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> that is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, both according to <hi>Grotius,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> whom you quote for your Authority in this Matter. Another Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may be this. The Lord Chriſt did ſuffer the Law accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you, that we may be freed from Puniſhment, and Chriſt obey'd the Law, that we might have right to Heaven. This I ſuppoſe, You (as repreſenting the <hi>Independent</hi> Brethren) do hold, and there is now this <hi>Commutation of Perſons</hi> here, that God does look on what Chriſt ſuffered and did for us, as done by Chriſt in our Perſons; and on what he did and ſuffered for us, to be done by us in his Perſon; or more ſhort, that, in what Chriſt did and ſuffered, God looks on it as done by Chriſt in <hi>Our</hi> Perſon, and by us in <hi>Christs</hi> Perſon. Here is a <hi>Change of Perſons</hi> who can gain ſay it? Eſpecially, if it be added (as you muſt hold) that without this we could not have, and by this we therefore have, Deliverance from Wrath, and Right to Salvation. If Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be not ours (you may urge) it cannot juſtifie us, and if it be ours, it can be ours in good earneſt in Law-ſenſe, no otherwiſe. This is high, but there is a Third Conſtruction goes farther; which is, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94658:8"/>as Chriſt ſtood in our Room, and put on our Perſon to ſuffer for us, ſo we are put into his Room to be Righteous for us, or put on his Perſon to ſtand before God for Juſtification and Life. Both theſe Conſtructions, whatſoever is made of them, are too much, and to be diſcarded upon the account of our Reaſons already mentioned, and yet more. There is no ſuch <hi>Commutation</hi> warrantable, but there are Texts wreſted to this Senſe, which muſt have another Interpretation. There is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, but makes us juſtifiable by the <hi>Law,</hi> which ſubverts the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> There is neither of them, but makes his Righteouſneſs to juſtifie us <hi>formaliter,</hi> or to be the <hi>formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification.</p>
            <p>This being therefore a fundamental Miſtake of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,</hi> and the firſt of theſe Conſtructions being the only true Conſtruction, it is fit I ſhould make Anſwer to all that ſeems weighty in both the other; and do ſay, that when Chriſt hath ſuffered for us, and obeyed the Law for us (which others wont ſay, but I do) that is, not <hi>bono nostro</hi> only, but <hi>loco nostro,</hi> in this Senſe, that by his Sufferings we are freed from <hi>Suffering,</hi> not <hi>Caſtigatory Puniſhments,</hi> but of the <hi>Curſe of the Law,</hi> and by his Obedience we are freed from that perfect obeying the Law required as the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Life, though not from obeying the Goſpel, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Faith and Repentance, and good Works in Sincerity in the room thereof, and hath not obeyed the Law for us, or in our ſtead otherwiſe; the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt conſiſting of both, his Sufferings and Obedience, is imputed to us, and made ours, though not <hi>in ſe,</hi> yet in the Effects; ſo that upon the account of his Righteouſneſs, or for his Sake, we are juſtified: This being ſaid, I have two things to Anſwer, one is in regard to your <hi>Phraſe</hi> as Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> calls it; the other is in regard to the <hi>Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For your <hi>Phraſe,</hi> Chriſt's ſuffering in our Perſon, may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſo as when we deſerved to die, he died in our rooms, that we might not ſuffer but be free from it according to the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: Or ſo, as that Good looks upon us to have ſuffered in him, as what our <hi>Attorney</hi> doth, we are in <hi>Law</hi> accounted our ſelves to have done, according to the other Conſtructions. In the <hi>first ſenſe,</hi> if you pleaſe, theſe Terms may be uſed, but not in the other. There are ſundry Reaſons intimated already for it, but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94658:9"/>this more eſpecially here at this time, becauſe it is contradictory to the firſt. If Chriſt hath ſuffered that we might not ſuffer, then hath he not ſuffered that God might look on us, as if we had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. To ſuffer that we might not ſuffer, and to ſuffer that we may be accounted to have ſuffered, is a contradiction</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Matter,</hi> I deny not, but hold, That it is through Chriſt's Righteouſneſs we are juſtified; yet that Faith and Repentance are not only required as the <hi>Condition,</hi> but when the Condition is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, it is our <hi>Goſpel-Righteouſneſs;</hi> ſo that though it be Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, is that <hi>propter quod,</hi> it is the Righteouſneſs of Faith, is that <hi>per quod</hi> we are juſtified. There is therefore here a double <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and twofold <hi>Concurrence</hi> to be diſtinguiſhed and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. The double Righteouſneſs is the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Christ,</hi> and Righteouſneſs of <hi>Faith;</hi> the double Concurrence is a Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>per modum meriti,</hi> or <hi>per modum cauſae formalis.</hi> Now the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, I muſt affirm, concurs <hi>per modum meriti,</hi> and the Righteouſneſs of Faith <hi>per modum Cauſae formalis,</hi> to our Juſtification.</p>
            <p>This is the Doctrine which, in oppoſition both to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the Abſurdity brought into it by the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> I do maintain, as you ſee in my late Book, and may ſee farther. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, That Juſtification is by the infuſion of Inherent Grace, and that <hi>Inherent Grace</hi> therefore is the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in oppoſition to them, ſay, That it is by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Christ</hi> we are juſtified, and that it is <hi>Christ's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs imputed,</hi> is the <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of it. I ſay, it is by neither of theſe, but by <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>Works,</hi> which is God's Gracious Condeſcention in his accepting of our Faith and imperfect Obedience through the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and Merit of Chriſt unto Life, that we be juſtified; and that it is <hi>Faith imputed for Righteouſneſs,</hi> is the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification. It is not then (I ſay) the <hi>infuſion</hi> of Faith and Grace into us (which diſtinguiſhes it from the <hi>Papiſts</hi>) but it is the <hi>imputing</hi> that Faith and Grace infuſed (which diſtinguiſhes it from the common <hi>Proteſtant</hi>) for Righteouſneſs, that is our <hi>formal</hi> Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>Alas Mr. <hi>Report!</hi> What an abſurd thing was it at firſt to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould hold, That a Sinner was made, or accounted <hi>Righteous</hi> without a Righteouſneſs, or by <hi>another's</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, whieh is all one as to be <hi>Learned</hi> with another's <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94658:9"/>or <hi>Holy</hi> by another's <hi>Holineſs.</hi> Now let me tell you in good earneſt, which perhaps you have never throughly reflected upon, that the ſame Abſurdity remains if we ſay, That we are <hi>Formaliter</hi> made Righteous, or <hi>Formaliter</hi> Juſtified by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, which our former Divines having taught, we muſt now leave them. And one thing more, which I am more ſure you never thought on, I will tell you, That the Doctrine which I ſubſtitute in the room of this, is that (I conjecture) which was indeed the very <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Luther,</hi> as appears by his words, and thoſe of his immediate Followers I have quoted in my Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. and 20. Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them conſiſts in two things, Faith in the Heart, or incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Obedience, and God's Imputation. Our Faith and inchoate Grace being imperfect, and ſo no Righteouſneſs according to the Law, God does for the ſake of Chriſt, or through his Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Merits accept of it ſo as by his Goſpel Law to impute (conſtitute and allow) it to us <hi>for Righteouſneſs,</hi> and thereby give us Right to <hi>Impunity</hi> and <hi>Salvation.</hi> This firſt true notion, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently digeſted by <hi>Luther,</hi> others ſeeking to advance, through the interpreting it by an application of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to the Believer's <hi>Perſon,</hi> inſtead of applying it to his <hi>Performance,</hi> came to pervert it, and our former Divines took it up, and ſtood upon it ſo much againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that <hi>Bellermine</hi> accounts the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> about <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtification</hi> to be as nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; and yet is this term <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> ſo much out of uſe of late in our preſent Divinity, that many of our Brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſenſible of their grand importance, as to the Negation of the Doctrine ſo held, and of the <hi>Abſurdity</hi> in the root, they do retain the Senſe without the Words, or at leaſt maintain ſo much of it as the reſt does follow, and yet do ſo ſeriouſly fall upon them that own the Conſequences, that I cannot wonder, if you, and that Brother of yours that have undertaken the cauſe, ſhould have ſuch a kind of Spirit rais'd in you, as was in <hi>Elihu,</hi> when he was angry with <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends, who were ready to accuſe him, when they had nothing they could ſay without blame in themſelves. <hi>Then was kindled the Wrath of Elihu, the Son of Barachael against Job, and against his three Friends was his Wrath kindled, becauſe they had found no anſwer, and yet had condemned Job.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one thing I will ſay therefore of that Brother of yours, which is more kind perhaps than others will, which is, That in that <hi>Language</hi> of his which is ſo <hi>harſh,</hi> and in that <hi>Matter</hi> (as quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94658:10"/>by others) which is ſo <hi>broad</hi> that they are beyond enduring, yet do I apprehend, methinks, a <hi>Zeal</hi> in the one, and an <hi>Integrity</hi> in the other. A Zeal in that Heat and Wrath he hath againſt any that ſhall gainſay a Doctrine which he hath imbibed from his Youth, and places his Salvation upon; and a ſincerity in that he being a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Man and ſeeing more deeply than others into the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it, he ſcorns to baulk any of them, and ſo is <hi>broad</hi> when others <hi>ſhift,</hi> which he, I perceive, abominates. And this does prompt me therefore to ſay ſomething in regard to <hi>you</hi> and <hi>him,</hi> and that <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Brother you both have writ againſt. In ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, I would ask all three, Whether before reading this, you had come to any ſuch Conſideration of this Matter, that if I had ask'd you the Queſtion, <hi>What is the Form, or Formal Cauſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,</hi> you would have given me a fix'd Anſwer to it? I do ſuppoſe you would acknowledge you had not, nor thought it ſo material to know. But you, and ſome greater Men than you, are out there. The Form of a Thing is that by which the Thing is, that which it is. If you know not the Form of Juſtification, you know not what Juſtification is, and when it may be known, and you don't know it; How can you tell (as another that does) what is right or wrong that you ſay about it? The Form does <hi>Dare</hi> the <hi>Nomen</hi> and the <hi>Eſſe,</hi> as it gives the Being, it denominates the Thing. <hi>Juſtificatus</hi> accordingly hath his <hi>Form</hi> paſſively denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him ſo from <hi>Juſtitia,</hi> and that Righteouſneſs which <hi>makes</hi> and <hi>denominates</hi> us Righteous, muſt be the <hi>Form</hi> of our Juſtification. Now what that Righteouſneſs is, I have here and in my Book diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed, and told it you as to my Opinion, and that of the common <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> And as for you then, and your Reverend Brother, who have, I ſuppoſe, taken up the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine, as formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, without queſtioning whether it were ſound at the bottom, or no; I would have you both, after my notice of its being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of our latter more conſiderate Divines, to exerciſe that Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, which that Brother has ſomething above others, in looking into thoſe <hi>Conſequences</hi> how far they do go; and then I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there is one of theſe two things he muſt come to, Either he will judge them maintainable, and the Doctrine good; and if ſo, let him go on, and ſee if he can make the <hi>Antinomian</hi> White: Or he will ſee the Conſequences ſuch, that he cannot come to that concluſion, and then he muſt reflect back on the Premiſes, and come to another, that the Doctrine muſt be changed; and if ſo,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94658:10"/>then retaining his Honeſty, that will not abide daubing, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I offer in the room of his, having nothing of that kind in it, and nothing I ſeek by it but Truth for Truth's ſake, may happily ſtand fair with him for the making a Convert, more likely, of one moſt extream from me, than of the Moderate and Wiſe, and conſequently the Cold, that unleſs it came into vogue, will never concern themſelves about it. And for that <hi>Noted Brother</hi> you two have wrote againſt, as differing from you in ſeveral things, eſpecially in a ſound Explication of ſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, oppoſing the Sentiments of your Brethren; which as in gave them high offence, ſo it ſtir'd up this Brother of yours to write vehemently againſt him, as a Perverter of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine; and verging towards <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> But he therein innocent, being not concern'd ſo much about that, as about the Doctrine he taught, that it might not offend, he did endeavour ſo to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it with Complyance and over yielding, that made me write againſt him, as like to yield away our Cauſe. I muſt inſtance in what particular. The <hi>Independent Brethren</hi> accuſed him for hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs was not imputed to us, but only in the Effects, when he had expreſly ſaid, That <hi>beſides the Effects the very Righteouſneſs of Christ is imputed to a Believer.</hi> Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Doctrine he otherwiſe maintain'd, he ſhould have held and owned that which the Brethren accuſed him for; but his Words were otherwiſe, and he thought (I believe) that his Words and Doctrine were conſiſtent, the Reaſon, indeed, being becauſe he had not, and fundamentally could not have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what Juſtification is; that is, he knew not then what the Form of it is, (nor could, my ſelf being the firſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> that have ventured here to ſpeak out) when yet it was to be known. If Chriſt's Righteouſneſs be imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> which thoſe Words ſay, then muſt God look upon us as Legally Righteous in him, and we Formally Juſtified by his Righteouſneſs, which with the Conſequence following, muſt drive him from his own Opinion and to come over to yours, and lead him farther even to that Party he hath wrote ſo well againſt in the Firſt of his deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commended Books: So that I have <hi>more</hi> than hopes from him (when I have <hi>hopes</hi> from you) that he will, becauſe he muſt, (if he writes again) come over to me, (or rather to the Apoſtle) in the point. <hi>To this end came I into the World</hi> (ſays our Saviour) <hi>that I might bear Witneſs to the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94658:11"/>
            <p>And here I will ſay ſomething to the Quick, in regard to Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> that conſiderable Brother, and you too; for I think both more worthy Men than you do of one another. I have told you before, That I believe if Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> had not ſeen my laſt Book, or thoſe Sheets, or my <hi>Half-ſheet</hi> forementioned; and I had ask'd him, or you, the Queſtion, What is the <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Formal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification? It is like he and you would have inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly acknowledged both, that you had not thought ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, or that it was ſcarce ſo pertinent as to be ask'd: But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is like to prove otherwiſe to him, I muſt after all I have writ, and his Thoughts on it, ask the Queſtion, <hi>What is the Form or Formal Cauſe of our Juſtification?</hi> I ſay, <hi>our</hi> Juſtification, which once for all I muſt tell you, does denote Juſtification <hi>Paſſively</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as it muſt be taken, and is by <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> in their Diſpute about it, and by the Apoſtle when he diſputes, That it is by Faith and not Works that <hi>Abraham</hi> was, and we are <hi>juſtified.</hi> If one ſay here Juſtification hath no form, he is beaten plainly off the Stage. Juſtification, it is true, <hi>Actively</hi> taken, is an Act of God, a Judicial Act of him as the <hi>Efficient,</hi> by the Goſpel as his <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> whereby he <hi>conſtitutes</hi> the ſound Believer <hi>Righteous,</hi> and thereby gives him a Right to Impunity and Glory. As Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then taken thus <hi>Actively,</hi> being an Act of God, Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> and you know (I ſuppoſe) that <hi>ex parte Agentis,</hi> it can be nothing but God's <hi>Will;</hi> and that his <hi>Will</hi> is his <hi>Eſſence;</hi> and that God acts only by his Eſſence; and that there can be no <hi>cauſe</hi> of, nor any <hi>new Act</hi> in God's Eſſence; and that it is in regard therefore to the <hi>Effect,</hi> as that <hi>Act</hi> is terminated on its <hi>Object,</hi> that God's <hi>Will</hi> hath that Denomination, ſo that it is of the <hi>Effect;</hi> [our being juſtified,] there are Cauſes, and a <hi>formal</hi> there muſt be as well as others. Whereas our <hi>Proteſtants</hi> now do maintain againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> That it is the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed is this <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe;</hi> I ask again of that Reverend Brother, Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> Whether, according to the common Doctrine, he does hold, That the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Christ</hi> imputed, and received by Faith alone, is the <hi>Form,</hi> formal cauſe, or reaſon of our Juſtification, yea or no? Here is a Queſtion, which is <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Divining Cup, that muſt tell, Whether Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> be a <hi>True Man,</hi> or a <hi>Spy?</hi> If he anſwers Categorically, either one or the other, he is a <hi>True Man:</hi> if he <hi>ſhuffles,</hi> he is a <hi>Spy.</hi> If then he ſays, yea, according to his Aſſertion, that <hi>Beſides the Effects, the very Righteouſneſs of Christ is imputed to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94658:11"/>the Believer,</hi> then does he come to you, as the Maintainer of the commonly received <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine, and you will be pleaſed, I hope, with ſuch a Proſelite: If he ſays <hi>No,</hi> then muſt he <hi>retract</hi> that ſaying, as the good Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> did Many, and come over to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and me, and be welcome to the <hi>Truth,</hi> as I judgé. As for you then Mr. <hi>Report,</hi> I muſt ask alſo the ſame Queſtion, (but not to have an Anſwer till you ſee I deſire it;) Whether you do really joyn with the common <hi>Proteſtant</hi> in this point, as to the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe</hi> of our Juſtification? If you ſay you do, you ſee the Conſequences. Take them all, draw out their Strength, try if you can anſwer them; One, and an Elder, Brother of yours forementioned, is ſo openly Honeſt as when he ſees, to avow them; but if you begin to ſhrug, and muſt leave him, I pray conſider where you can ſtop, unleſs you come to a <hi>Third</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for you and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> to reconcile in, when you have both beaten one another out of your Own.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Report,</hi> before I end, I cannot but ſpeak to you of one or two things, becauſe I look on you as one that have been as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward formerly as any for compoſing <hi>Theſes</hi> for Agreement, and I am moved at thoſe <hi>Nine Articles</hi> which Mr. <hi>Rebuke</hi> mentions upon the Reſarciation of the firſt Breach among the Brethren, whereof the <hi>Fifth</hi> is of <hi>Juſtification;</hi> in which, there are (allowing the reſt as unqueſtionable) theſe Words; <hi>Not imputing Faith it ſelf the Act of Believing, or any other Evangelical Obedience to them as their Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> which Words are ſuch, that if you had taken care on purpoſe to ſay ſomething for contradicting the Scripture, you could not have done your Work more effectually. <hi>Not by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting Faith it ſelf,</hi> (ſay you) <hi>the Act of Believing, to them, for their Righteouſneſs;</hi> when the Scripture ſays expreſly, <hi>Abraham believed God, and it</hi> (it, that Act of Believing) <hi>was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> Again, <hi>Not by imputing the Act of any Obedience;</hi> when the Scripture ſays expreſly, <hi>Then ſtood up</hi> Phinehas, <hi>and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted Judgment, and it was counted to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> How could you find in your Heart, Brother, eſpecially how could thoſe of your <hi>Independent Brethren,</hi> that out of oppoſition to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that Holy and Excellent Man Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who found fault with this in the <hi>Savoy Confeſſion,</hi> find in their Hearts to compoſe, or cauſe to be compoſed ſuch an Article for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of both Parties? What my Reverend Brethren! Are you for a plain Conſpiracy againſt the Holy Scripture? What
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94658:12"/>cauſe have I therefore for this Doctrine of mine (not before throughly handled) to contradict you? The Lord of Truth be Witneſs between us. You may ſay, That not only the <hi>Savoy Confeſſion,</hi> but the <hi>Aſſemblies Confeſſion</hi> and <hi>Catechiſms</hi> do counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſo much: I anſwer, If not only the Miniſters at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> but an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> nay the Miniſters of the whole Earth could joyn in drawing up the Article of Juſtification in theſe <hi>Words,</hi> they muſt be all laid flat on their Backs by <hi>thoſe</hi> of the Apoſtle, <hi>And it was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> Upon this account that I could not ſubſcribe my ſelf to ſuch an Article, I muſt add, as to your way of Concord by <hi>Theſes,</hi> I like it not. For though a <hi>Church</hi> that is Eſtabliſh'd by Authority, where the Preacher is anſwerable for his Doctrine to his Superiours, may by ſuch means be upheld, by their taking care that Holy Mother does <hi>nihil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimenti capere,</hi> it is not ſo with the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> whoſe Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing depends on their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and they ſo divided: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not a Union in <hi>Doctrinals,</hi> I apprehend, but a Union in <hi>Practicals</hi> and in <hi>Love</hi> that is adviſeable; and that, not without the leaving every Man (acknowledging only the Holy Scriptures and the Three Creeds) to the Liberty of their own Opinions.</p>
            <p>I have no more now but to let you know, that whereas the deſign of this Letter being the ſame with that of my Books, the <hi>Middle Way,</hi> my <hi>Pacification,</hi> my <hi>Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel,</hi> there is a new Book on the Point coming out, or come out by the Reverend and Learned Mr. <hi>Clark,</hi> known by his <hi>Annotations</hi> upon the Old and New Teſtament; upon the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof there hath paſſed many Letters between him and me for the clearing this <hi>Middle Way</hi> which we take, or to ſome Difficulties appearing in it, which Letters I intend (as far as is fit) to Print, and this Paper being ſome Abſtract of the Senſe (which I could not have thus ſuddenly wrote, if I had not been thereby furniſhed) though fully comprehended by my ſelf, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken in by others ſo fully as by thoſe Letters which have their Enlargement, and came more naturally from me; and therefore I deſire you to ſuſpend your Judgment as to the main great Matter, or <hi>Article,</hi> till you have read theſe Letters alſo, which I do purpoſe to ſhew to you and to Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> before I Print them; becauſe I think that he ſo far as he differs from me, and you too are both out, and can be reconciled never but by a <hi>Third way</hi> between you that I propoſe; and if that be <hi>Truth,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94658:12"/>I do believe ſo worthily of you both, that either of you will think it a greater Victory to yield to the Truth, than to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one another.</p>
            <p>The Title of theſe Letters, when Printed, (which I hope you will find them make good) ſhall be this. <hi>Letters between Mr.</hi> John Humfrey <hi>and Mr.</hi> Samuel Clark, <hi>in reference to the Point of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Written upon the Occaſion of Mr.</hi> Clark's <hi>Printing his Book on that Subject, before it came out, and Publiſhed by Conſent, for the Vindication of that Doctrine wherein they agree, as ſound, by ſhewing the Difference of it from that of the</hi> Papiſt, <hi>and the miſtake of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Proteſtant. <hi>In order to an impartial and more full <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that great Article, by the Improvement of that whereto they have attained, or Correction of any thing wherein they err, by better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having finiſht here that which I intended for Four Sheets with the <hi>Half Sheet</hi> at the End; the Printer gave me Notice, that there would be a Leaf or two wanting to be fill'd.</p>
            <p>After thus much then (there being more to be ſaid) I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Mr. <hi>Report,</hi> that there is nothing wherein you can pinch Me, and Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> more than by fixing on this one thing, which I ſuppoſe you do; that a <hi>Commutation,</hi> a <hi>Subſtitution,</hi> or <hi>Surro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of one Perſon in the room of another, for the Doing or Suffering any thing in his behalf, muſt imply the Doing or Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering that <hi>very thing,</hi> which the other was to do or ſuffer, or elſe it is no ſtrict or proper <hi>Subſtitution;</hi> and conſequently, that Chriſt (as you hold) bearing the very Puniſhment of our Sins, we are to be counted in him (as our <hi>Surrogate</hi>) to have our ſelves born that Puniſhment; ſeeing what is done by a <hi>Surrogate</hi> or <hi>Subſtitute</hi> is reckoned in Law, to have been done by him for whom he hath Officiated. Likewiſe Chriſt having obeyed the Law for us, we are to be reckoned to have obeyed; and ſo to be Righteous in his Righteouſneſs, and Juſtified by it. For my ſpeaking therefore ſomething more to this; we muſt conſider there are Terms uſed by Divines and in Scripture (as that of <hi>Surety,</hi> once) which we are not to take <hi>Strictly</hi> and ſlaviſhly in their Vulgar Conception; for that were rude, coarſe, and raw to do ſo; but they muſt be <hi>Largely,</hi> generouſly Conſtrued, with the Liberty of more Accurateneſs and Conſonancy to the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Faith; and conſequently to be underſtood (as in our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicks
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94658:13"/>we have it) <hi>Pro ut prudens deſinierit.</hi> Upon which account I muſt anſwer, that foraſmuch as you have taken theſe Terms from <hi>Grotius;</hi> it is fit, it is reaſonable, you ſhould alſo take his <hi>Senſe</hi> and meaning of them; and that is ſuch (which you know well enough) that though he does account that there is a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation,</hi> and <hi>Surrogation</hi> of Chriſt's Perſon in our room in Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for us, that we may be freed from the Puniſhment; yet does he not underſtand it ſo, as that Chriſt did undergo the very ſame Puniſhment as due to us by the Law (and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your Argument failes you) but that it was an <hi>Equivalent</hi> to it; That it was not the <hi>Idem,</hi> but the <hi>Tantundem;</hi> That it was <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> not <hi>Payment.</hi> That which <hi>Grotius</hi> vindicates is, Chriſts <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> and if Chriſt had paid the <hi>very Debt,</hi> it would deſtroy <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> The Law was not <hi>executed</hi> on our Surety, nor on Us, but Chriſt ſatisfied the <hi>Lawgiver</hi> (not the <hi>Law</hi>) that it might <hi>not</hi> be executed; and ſeeing he did ſo, he did it not therefore, that God ſhould look on us, as if we had our ſelves been puniſhed. The Puniſhment the Law threatned, was on the Perſon that ſinned, <hi>Noxa caput ſequitur:</hi> But when Sinleſs Chriſt ſuffers, as that is not the <hi>Perſon,</hi> ſo that is not the <hi>Thing</hi> which is in the Threat, but while <hi>alius ſoluit aliud ſoluitur,</hi> as <hi>Grotius</hi> before has it. The Puniſhment threatned by the Law, includes a <hi>Deprivation of Gods Favour,</hi> as well as <hi>Pain,</hi> but Chriſt was not capable of that, nor of Etarnal Wrath. Beſides, it is not <hi>this Law</hi> that could lay any Obligation of Suffering on Chriſt that was not <hi>Obnoxious,</hi> but his Obligation aroſe from the <hi>Law proper to him;</hi> the Law of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> and his voluntary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking to make God Satisfaction. It was not <hi>ex delicto,</hi> but <hi>ex contractu,</hi> as you know our Divines ſay. And conſequently, it was <hi>an</hi> Obligation, not <hi>our</hi> Obligation to the Puniſhment he took on him. If the very Debt we owed had been paid by us, or our Surety, then could there have been no <hi>Pardon.</hi> Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Pardon are contraries. If a Man be puniſhed or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Law (in himſelf or <hi>Subſtituto</hi>) he is not Pardoned: If he be pardoned, he is not puniſhed. This Suffering of Chriſt then for us, muſt not be the <hi>ſame</hi> as the Law inflicts, but an <hi>Equivalent,</hi> and ſuch as God might have <hi>refuſed to take,</hi> which makes it <hi>Satisfaction</hi> (not <hi>Payment</hi>), and us capable of <hi>Pardon.</hi> This Doctrine of Pardon upon Satisfaction, is the ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine propugned by <hi>Grotius.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94658:13"/>
            <p>Thus much then for your Doctrine, now for Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> who agrees ſo much with me. Our Doctrine is this, that Chriſt's Obeying and Suffering in our ſtead admits of two Senſes.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>So in our Stead, as that God exacteth not from us that doing or ſuffering, yet gives us the Benefit of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>So in our Stead as that we are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally reputed to do and ſuffer what Christ did, as one Civil Perſon with him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
In the <hi>first</hi> Senſe, that Chriſt obeyed the Law, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our ſtead, we all agree: In the <hi>ſecond</hi> Senſe, I and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> deny it, and you hold it. Here then may you argue, and I argue. That which you may argue is. If according to us, Chriſt obeyed and ſuffered <hi>not</hi> in our ſtead, ſo as to be one legal Perſon with us, then cannot what he did and ſuffered be legally, Ours, and then cannot his Righteouſneſs be imputed to us <hi>in ſe,</hi> but in the <hi>Effects</hi> only. But Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> ſays, <hi>Beſides the Effects the very Righteouſneſs of Christ is imputed to Believers.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> muſt Anſwer. That which I argue is. If according to you, Chriſt <hi>did</hi> obey and ſuffer in our Stead, as one Civil or Legal Perſon with us, then as we have his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to <hi>Juſtifie</hi> us, we muſt have it to <hi>Redeem</hi> us. He that is made of God our <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> is made our <hi>Redemption.</hi> But we have it not, it is not ours, to <hi>Redeem</hi> us, and therefore not to <hi>Juſtifie</hi> us; or therefore it is not, it cannot be <hi>in ſe</hi> imputed to us for our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> This you muſt Anſwer. For my part now, I ſuppoſe neither of you can, but that you muſt come off; And if ſo, not you to him, or he to you, but both to me, or to that <hi>Third</hi> way I have propoſed; and do yet propoſe to your farther Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>That the Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel, is that Righteouſneſs which Juſtifies us, there is none do Queſtion; but what this Righteouſneſs is, is the Queſtion. <hi>But now is the Righteouſneſs of God without the Law made manifeſt.</hi> It cannot be Chriſts Righteouſneſs, for this is a Righteouſneſs <hi>with the Law,</hi> a perfect Conformity to the whole Law; when this is an incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate imperfect Righteouſneſs, that according to the <hi>Law</hi> is none, but made a Righteouſneſs by the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> In another Place the Apoſtle has it, <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God in him;</hi> in or through Chriſt, and therefore not <hi>his.</hi> But how of God? If not that of <hi>Christ,</hi> who is <hi>God?</hi> No, for <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> there are two; But of Gods Ordination, becauſe this is the Way or Method of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Righteous, that God hath ordained <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder</hi> the Goſpel, as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94658:14"/>Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> expreſſes it; though I ſhould rather ſay, <hi>According</hi> to the Goſpel, for no doubt this Righteouſneſs was under the Law, and ever in the World, or elſe no Man could have been ſaved. The Apoſtle therefore, after he hath ſaid <hi>without the Law,</hi> does yet adde, <hi>being witneſſed by the Law and Prophets.</hi> And what <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> is that, which hath this <hi>Witneſs?</hi> There never was Man under the Law, I am perſwaded, that thought he was Righteous by anothers Righteouſneſs, or that the Obedience of the Life and Death of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, was imputed to him as his Righteouſneſs; whereby God held him, and dealt with him as a Righteous Perſon. What Man of free Thought can believe that? But if, by the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> we underſtand his Grace and Condeſcenſion to every ſincere Perſon, that walked uprightly before him in accepting them to Life, notwithſtanding their failings, when yet they knew not upon what account it was, as we under the Goſpel; This without Queſtion, we have every where <hi>witneſſed</hi> in the Old Teſtament. There is no Place where any Pious Soul applies it ſelf to God for his Favour, with Faith or Truſt in his Goodneſs or Mercy, when yet he knew that if God ſhould deal with him in Severity, he could not by the Law be juſtified, but that Place is a moſt evident witneſs of this <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> That Place, which ſpeaks of the <hi>Word</hi> to be <hi>Nigh</hi> them, and <hi>in their Heart</hi> (which is the <hi>Word of Faith,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle) does witneſs it. Any Place or Places, where God Promiſes to write the Law in their Hearts, or give them a new Heart, or put a Fear, or Love, in their Heart, if to the end that they may be ſaved; Any Place or Places where it is ſaid of the Righteous, that they <hi>ſhall Live in their Righteouſneſs;</hi> And that Place, which ſays, the Righteous ſhall <hi>Live by Faith,</hi> do all witneſs to this <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which otherwhere is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd <hi>the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith,</hi> and <hi>the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith;</hi> Faith it ſelf, which is ſound and <hi>Works by Love</hi> (that is all one with Evangelical Obedience) being that, which for Chriſt's ſake God <hi>imputes</hi> to us <hi>for Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that is, our <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe here my Sheets will be fill'd, and that I have room for no more, but this Prayer; That it may pleaſe the God of Truth to inlighten you by the Scripture, ſo as to have the Knowledge, and ſuch a Senſe of this <hi>Righteouſneſs of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94658:14"/>God</hi> on your Spirit, that falling down and Bleſing his Name with me, from the bottom of your Heart for this, that it is not by a <hi>Righteouſneſs of Works,</hi> but by a Righteouſneſs, the failings whereof are pardoned, and the little (how little ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if ſincere) done, accepted through Chriſt's Satisfaction and Merits, that we are juſtified; you may <hi>receive the Truth,</hi> in the Experience and <hi>Love</hi> of it, firſt in your ſelf, and then improve it to the good of others, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your True Friend and Servant in Chriſt, <hi>JOHN H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MFREY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94658:15"/>
            <head>The <hi>Half-ſheet,</hi> Writ in Reference to the Paper Printed by Mr. <hi>Report.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Book of Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> called <hi>Goſpel Truths,</hi> there are two Expreſſions which the Brethren would have him Retract: One is, <hi>There is not a Change of Perſon between Christ and the Elect.</hi> The other is, <hi>The Father was never diſpleaſed with Christ.</hi> I will humbly motion here a drawn Battel, or mutual Condeſcention; that is, for Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> to withdraw one of theſe Paſſages they except againſt; and, for the Brethren to withdraw the other Exception.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt Paſſage, whatſoever is to be underſtood by <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of Perſons,</hi> the Brethren underſtand thus much, That Chriſt <hi>put on the Perſon of Sinners,</hi> for theſe are their Words. Now Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> I ſuppoſe, denies this, and they would have him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract his Denial. By <hi>Perſon</hi> therefore we are to conſider, that two things may be ſignified, the Perſon of the Sinner himſelf, <hi>Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum rationale;</hi> or the <hi>Quality</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> of a Sinner, as, when a Man acts a Drunkard on the Stage, he perſonates Drunkenneſs; if a King, he perſonates Majeſty. Chriſt, GOD-Man, ſtood in the room of us Sinners, in what he did and ſuffer'd for us, <hi>quatenus</hi> He and we are <hi>Suppoſita rationalia,</hi> and in this firſt ſence of the Word, Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> allows a <hi>Commutation of Perſons,</hi> ſo as when the <hi>Suffering</hi> was <hi>Christ's,</hi> the <hi>Benefit</hi> was <hi>Ours,</hi> which is that <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> intends only againſt the <hi>Socinians.</hi> But. Mr. <hi>Williams denies</hi> that Chriſt took upon him the <hi>Quality</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> of Sinners, which is that Doctrine he ſuppoſe Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> to <hi>maintain;</hi> and that is, in the ſecond ſence of the Word, he denies what they affirm, to wit, That <hi>He put on the Perſon of Sinners.</hi> Chriſt did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent or act the part of Sinners, nor was look'd on by God as a Sinner, when our Surety: A <hi>commutatio Hominum</hi> there was, no <hi>commutatio Actionum.</hi> He repreſented <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> that are Sinners, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented not <hi>the Sinner.</hi> A Sinner is one that breaks the Law of God, and Chriſt did not ſo, he acted no ſuch Part, and God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94658:15"/>accounted that he did; and there is therefore no <hi>Change of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Diſtinction of theſe Terms is not made, ſo far as I know, by any Divines, (which excuſes the Brethrens Citation of one for the other) but I uſe it as peculiar for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining Mr. <hi>Williams</hi>'s Sence, ſo that if any ſhall ſtill chuſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them, and expreſs our Sence otherwiſe, it is all one to me, and may be to him.</note> 
               <hi>Perſon,</hi> though a <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> according to Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi> When in this ſence therefore of the Word <hi>Perſon</hi> he is in the right, let us conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to the other ſence of it, (as it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies our Humane Nature, not our Sinful Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Sinful Qualities) that tho' Chriſt did <hi>ſuſtain our Perſons</hi> (giving the Brethren liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch Words) as to what he did and ſuffer'd in our ſtead, yet there is no one ſuch thing wherein we reciprocally <hi>ſuſtain his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> as he did <hi>ours;</hi> nothing whereby we are to be ſaid or accounted to have done what he did; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do I in my late Book, (<hi>Pacif. pag.</hi> 39.) ſay, That here is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Change of <hi>Perſon,</hi> but not of <hi>Perſons.</hi> A ſtrange thing real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that when the ſame Sence is intended by me and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> the ſame Diſtinction uſed, and both ſay true, yet the Terms of that Diſtinction are contrarily apply'd by us. I muſt deſire Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> therefore to conſider, whether the uſe of the Word <hi>Perſon</hi> be not foreign to our Divines, and it were not better to put what he means in ſuch Terms as are eaſier of reception, and that may be only by diſtinguiſhing of Chriſt's taking on him our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or bearing our Sins, in regard to the <hi>Fault,</hi> or the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and to ſay, he ſuſtained not our Perſons, or took on him our Sins <hi>quoad reatum culpae</hi> (in theſe known Words) ſo as to be accounted of God a Sinner; but <hi>quoad reatum poenae propter culpam noſtram,</hi> ſo only as voluntarily oblig'd to our Puniſhment. Here is the ſame thing in ſence, and if ſo good an end as Re-union might be obtained by it, he may (underſtanding with me) retract the Words in his Book, <hi>[There is not a Change of Perſon]</hi> and grant a <hi>Change of Perſon,</hi> ſo long as he maintains ſtill no <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> for his buſineſs is done thereby as well as by his ſticking to a <hi>Word.</hi> The Lord Jeſus, in what he did and ſuffer'd for us, <hi>ſuſtained our Perſons,</hi> (I give way to ſuch Phraſes for Peace) inſomuch as we ſtill ſay, That what he did and ſuffer'd for us was accounted by God as done and ſuffer'd in our room, that we might have the Benefit of it; but not accounted by him as if we had done and ſuffer'd in Chriſt's Perſon what he did and ſuffer'd for us; and ſo, in that reſpect, is there a <hi>Change of Perſon,</hi> but not of <hi>Perſons;</hi> whereby I mean plainly, not ſuch a Change as to make Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94658:16"/>
               <hi>Legally</hi> or in Law-ſence <hi>Ours,</hi> (or to be imputed <hi>in ſe,</hi> for that, let Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> know, is all one) which whoever affirms (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Shifts) let him be in as great Eſteem as he will, I ſay, he ſpeaks it in Ignorance hitherto of what this draws after it; To wit, that (beſides the Conſequences I ſhew, <hi>Pacif. pag.</hi> 36.) he makes us to be juſtified by Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, <hi>per modum cauſae formalis,</hi> which is an unadviſed, abſurd, and dangerous Poſition, as that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of our former great Divines, which gave the riſe to <hi>Antinomianiſm.</hi> Be it known therefore to the deſervedly-beloved Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> and the deſervedly-envied Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> (for there muſt be <hi>ſomething</hi> overtopping others in the Man, <hi>which</hi> is envied,) and the Worthy Brethren that drew, or ſigned this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that here is the Point which (I believe) they have not bent their Minds to ſearch into, ſo far as to be willing to ſpeak out, and tell me if I ask, When Faith, which is our Evangelical Perſonal Righteouſneſs, does concur ſome way with the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to our Juſtification, and Chriſt's Righteouſneſs (we know) does concur <hi>ſub genere cauſae Efficientis procatarcticae</hi> (and <hi>Materia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> alſo with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>per modum Meriti,</hi> and no otherwiſe: What is then, let any one of them tell me, <hi>That</hi> wherein <hi>the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Juſtification is to be placed, or can Juſtification be, or<note n="*" place="margin">Juſtificationis for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam juſtitia conſtare certum eſt: <hi>A Middle Way therefore here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi> Proteſtant <hi>and</hi> Papiſt, deſideratur.</note> 
               <hi>conſtare,</hi> without <hi>Any?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this Advice now, which (according to my Natural Genius) <hi>I</hi> ſhould have given to Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> (See 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> iii. 15.) <hi>I</hi> apprehend not prejudicial to <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> if his Sence is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, that is; the Truth of his Book, while the Quarrel about the <hi>Word</hi> be compos'd. It is plain, that Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> and They, hold the ſame thing; for he is no <hi>Socinian,</hi> but holds, Chriſt died <hi>for us</hi> in the Sence of <hi>in our ſtead;</hi> That he was our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting a Surrogation of Chriſt's Perſon in our room, when he became a Sacrifice for us, which is as much (<hi>I</hi> ſay again) as <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> to whom they appeal, did intend. It is nothing therefore, in my eſteem, for Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> to withdraw an Expreſſion in that ſence which offends, ſeeing in the <hi>Antinomian</hi> ſenſe, wherein he denies a Change of <hi>Perſon,</hi> the Brethren agree in the <hi>Negative</hi> with him; and in the <hi>Orthodox</hi> ſence, which they <hi>own,</hi> Mr. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> agrees in the <hi>Affirmative</hi> with them. It is not Baſe here, but Generous, and to be Victor to give way; it being enough that they both have declared themſelves. Beſides, if the Brethren be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94658:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>in earneſt to ſearch into the Matter, and would order their Words ſo as we might come to Concord both in Words and Sence, <hi>I</hi> have chalked out here, from my late Book, this Accommodation: <hi>I</hi> will allow them a <hi>Change of Perſon</hi> in the Orthodox ſence of the Word, ſo as to grant Chriſt did <hi>ſuſtain our Perſon</hi> in what he did and ſuffer'd; And they ſhall allow to me, that there is not a <hi>Change of Perſons,</hi> ſo as God did look on us to have done in Chriſt's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon what he did, tho' he did it in our behalf; and they ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth frame their Words accordingly. And that our Brethren may bend to ſome Reconciliation in this Propoſal, <hi>I</hi> do find, ſince <hi>I</hi> wrote my <hi>Pacification,</hi> the ſame Conception in Dr. <hi>Owen, We do not ſay, that God judgeth or eſteemeth that we did and ſuffer'd in our Perſons what Christ did and ſuffer'd; but only that he did it and ſuffer'd it in our ſtead.</hi> Of Juſtiſ. pag. 295.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>latter</hi> Paſſage, That <hi>the Father was never diſpleaſed with Christ;</hi> thus much muſt be premiſed and underſtood from what is ſaid on the <hi>former;</hi> That in the ſence he ſuſtain'd our <hi>Perſons</hi> he was <hi>made Sin for us,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, though <hi>he knew no Sin,</hi> that is to be underſtood <hi>Effectivè.</hi> He was not <hi>made Sin</hi> or a <hi>Sinner formaliter,</hi> but I ſay <hi>effectivè,</hi> in regard to the Effect of Sin, that is the bearing our Puniſhment, as before. Our Saviour therefore may be conſider'd as bearing <hi>our Perſons</hi> (according to theſe Brethren) and ſo our Sins; or in his <hi>own Perſon.</hi> God could not be diſpleaſed with him in the one, no, nor in the other Conſideration, becauſe it was of his own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. God, in the Puniſhment <hi>on</hi> his Son (not <hi>of</hi> his Son) was diſpleaſed with the <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Sinners</hi> whoſe Perſon he bare, but he was never diſpleaſed with the <hi>Perſon of his Son,</hi> and much leſs now, when he was fulfilling the Command of his Father, <hi>in giving himſelf for us an Offering and a Sacrifice of a ſweet-ſmelling Savour unto him.</hi> He muſt have a witty Invention, <hi>I</hi> think, that can find any thing to make himſelf differ from Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> in this Point. And what, when <hi>they</hi> and <hi>he</hi> agree in <hi>Sence,</hi> would our Brethren have Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> retract theſe <hi>Words?</hi> Nay, it is <hi>They</hi> muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw here, or they may bid him next go contradict the voice of God from Heaven, <hi>This is my Beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:94658:17"/>
            <head>Theſe Books written by the Reverend Author Mr. <hi>John Humfrey:</hi> And to be Sold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> &amp;c. are as follow.</head>
            <p>SEveral Papers about Four or Five Sheets apiece, called the <hi>Middle Way,</hi> of Election, of Redemption, of Juſtification, of the Covenants, Law and Goſpel, of Perfection, with indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency between the Orthodox and <hi>Quaker:</hi> As alſo Peaceable Diſquiſitions, which treat of the Natural and Spiritual Man, of Praying by the Spirit, of Preaching by Demonſtration of it, of Aſſurance, of the <hi>Arminian</hi> Grace, of the Poſſibility of <hi>Heathens</hi> Salvation, of the Reconciliation of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Jamos,</hi> of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs with other incidental Matters: One of which middle Papers, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That of Juſtification was Reprinted two Years ſince, with the Quotation of what concerns that Subject, out of the other; and ſince that one Sheet (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) and his Six Sheets laſt Year called <hi>Pacification,</hi> in which there is the Caſe of Non-Reſiſtance and Paſſive-Obedience ſtated and reſolved, the Doctrine whereof abjured in the two former Reigns, is here in this Kings Reign Recorded for a <hi>Memoriae Sacrum</hi> to thoſe which are to come. <hi>4to's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Righteouſneſs of God revealed in the Goſpel, or an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Enquiry into the genuine Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the great, but much controverted Article of Juſtification. To which is prefixt the Epiſtles of the Right Reverend the Biſhops of <hi>Ely, Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Cheſter. 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Private Pſalter or Manual of Devotion, compoſed by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter under the Apprehenſion of the Stone. <hi>8to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Axe laid to the Root of Separation, or the Churches cauſe againſt it. <hi>8to.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
